[Music]
this is a graph of mortality versus
coffee consumption suggesting coffee
drinkers live longer than non- coffee
drinkers this may be because coffee may
have beneficial effects on inflammation
lung function insulin sensitivity and
depression this may be in part because
of a class of polyphenol phytonutrients
found in coffee beans called chlorogenic
acids proven to have favorable effects
with studies like these where they just
give it alone in pill form and can show
beneficial effects such as acute blood
pressure lowering activity dropping the
top and bottom blood pressure numbers
within hours of
consumption okay so which coffee has the
most uh we know how to choose the
reddest tomato the deepest orange sweet
potato since many of the plant pigments
are the antioxidants themselves how do
you choose the healthiest coffee more
than a hundred coffees were tested and
different coffees had different caffeine
levels but the chlorogenic acid levels
varied by more than 30 fold as a
consequence coffee selection may have a
large influence of the potential Health
potential of coffee intake so all those
studies that show that you know one cup
of coffee does this or that I mean what
does that even mean when coffee can vary
so greatly interestingly the major
contributor to the wide range was the
coffee purchased from Starbucks which
had an extremely low chlorogenic acid
content averaging 10 times lower than
the
others maybe it's because they roast
their beans too dark the more you roast
the less there is they appear to be
partially destroyed by roasting caffeine
is pretty stable but a dark roast May
wipe out nearly 90% of the chlorogenic
acid content of the beans the difference
between a medium light roast and a
medium roast were not enough though to
make a difference in total antioxidant
status in people's bloodstream after
drinking them they both gave about the
same boost other factors such as how you
prepare it or decaffeination don't
appear to have a major effect what about
adding milk longtime fans may remember
this ancient video where the addition of
milk was shown to prevent the protective
effects of tea on artery function drink
black tea and you get a significant
Improvement in vascular function within
hours whereas addition of milk
completely blunted the effects of the
tea here's the big boost in artery
function you get drinking tea but drink
the same amount of tea with milk and
it's like you never drank the tea at
all they think it's the casine to blame
one of the milk proteins binding up the
tea phytonutrients bottom line This
finding that the tea induced Improvement
in vascular function is completely
attenuated after addition of milk may
have broad implications on the mode of
tea preparation and consumption in other
words maybe we should not add milk to
tea or put cream on our berries it
appears to have the same effect on Berry
phytonutrients or chocolate check this
out eat milk chocolate and nothing much
happens to the antioxidant power of your
bloodstream but eat dark chocolate and
get a nice Spike within an hour of
consumption yeah but is that just
because the milk in milk chocolate
crowds out some of the antioxidant Rich
cocoa milk chocolate may only be like
20% cocoa whereas a good dark chocolate
may be like 70% or more cocoa solids no
it's not just that here's how much of
this cocoa phytonutrient you get into
your bloodstream eating dark chocolate
compared to milk chocolate but eat that
same amount of dark chocolate with a
glass of milk and it blocks about
half okay that's cocoa beans what about
coffee beans
when milk was added to the coffee in
like a test tube antioxidant activity
decreased by more than half with just a
splash of milk and down like 95% in like
latte or something with lots of milk
okay but what happens in a test tube
doesn't necessarily happen in a person I
mean you don't know until you put it to
the test and indeed over the course of a
day significantly fewer chlorogenic
acids made it into people's bloodstream
drinking coffee with milk compared to
Black cutting absorption by more than
half what about soy milk in a test tube
coffee F A nutrients do appear to bind
not only the dairy proteins but also egg
and soy proteins you can see how they
did this like computer modeling showing
how these coffee compounds can dock
inside the nooks and crannies of dairy
egg white and soy proteins uh but what
happens in a test tube or computer
simulation doesn't necessarily happen in
a person eggs haven't been put to the
testy don't know if like having omelets
with your black coffee could impair
absorption and neither has soy milk
until
now yeah either way soy milk has some
inherent benefits over cow milk but does
it have the same nutrient blocking
effects and the answer is no no
significant difference in the absorption
of coffee phytonutrients drinking coffee
black or with soy milk what seemed to be
happening is that the soy proteins do
initially bind the coffee compounds up
in the small intestine but then your
good bacteria can release them so they
can be absorbed down in the lower
intestine so considering the reversible
nature of binding as opposed to the
dairy proteins it seems not to be as
relevant as to whether or not you add
soy
[Music]
milk for